<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>From The River · Archive Updates</title>
    <link>https://fromtheriver.org</link>
    <description>Latest additions to the From The River archive.</description>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Birwa]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-birwa</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-birwa</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A significant Palestinian Arab village with a history stretching back to the Roman period, al-Birwa was known for its olive groves, two schools (one for boys, one for girls), a mosque, a church, and its revered village shrine. It gained cultural prominence as the birthplace of the Palestinian national poet, Mahmoud Da…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-birwa.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Damun]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-damun</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-damun</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Situated on the Acre plain, al-Damun was a village with deep historical roots, containing ancient architectural remains and the shrine of the prophet Dhu al-Kifl, mentioned in the Qur'an. Its economy was primarily agricultural, focused on grains, olives, and melons, supplemented by the weaving of mats from nearby rush…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-damun.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Sumayriyya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-sumayriyya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-sumayriyya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A coastal village north of Acre, known to the Crusaders as 'Someleria,' al-Sumayriyya's economy was based on agriculture, particularly citrus and bananas, and stone quarrying from its ancient caves. The village was captured on May 14, 1948, by the Haganah's Carmeli Brigade during Operation Ben-Ami, an offensive design…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-sumayriyya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Bassa]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-bassa</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-bassa</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Bassa was a large and prosperous mixed Muslim and Christian village in northern Galilee, a hub of social and economic life with two schools, a large church, and a mosque. It was captured on May 14, 1948, during Operation Ben-Ami. After a brief battle, the village leaders surrendered. According to survivor testimoni…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-bassa.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Tira]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-tira</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-tira</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Known as 'Tira of the almonds' (Tirat al-Lawz), this was one of the largest and most important villages in the Haifa sub-district, with a history dating to the Roman era. It was a major producer of olives and oil, with several modern presses. Al-Tira faced a series of attacks beginning in December 1947, including a de…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-tira.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ayn Ghazal]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/ayn-ghazal</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/ayn-ghazal</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Ayn Ghazal was part of the 'Little Triangle' of resilient villages south of Haifa that held out against Zionist forces for months after the fall of the city. The village, which had a history of resistance dating back to the 1936-39 Arab revolt, was finally captured on July 26, 1948, during Operation Shoter ('Operation…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/ayn-ghazal.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ijzim]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/ijzim</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/ijzim</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A large and ancient village in the 'Little Triangle' with Ayn Ghazal, Ijzim had a history dating back to the Roman period and was home to a mosque, a church, and a shrine for a local sage. It was a center of steadfast resistance, holding out for months against Israeli encroachment. It finally fell on July 26, 1948, du…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/ijzim.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Tantura]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-tantura</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-tantura</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[An ancient coastal fishing village built on the ruins of the Canaanite city of Dor, al-Tantura had a vibrant economy based on fishing, agriculture, and trade. It was captured on the night of May 22-23, 1948, by the Haganah's Alexandroni Brigade during Operation Namal ('Operation Port'). Following its surrender, a larg…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-tantura.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ein Karem]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/ein-karem</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/ein-karem</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A prosperous and picturesque village west of Jerusalem, Ein Karem holds deep significance in Christian tradition as the birthplace of John the Baptist. It was a mixed Muslim and Christian community with several churches, monasteries, and a mosque. Its fate was sealed by the fall of surrounding villages and the terror…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/ein-karem.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Salama]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/salama</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/salama</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A large and densely populated village east of Jaffa, Salama had strong commercial ties to the city and a vibrant community with two schools and two mosques. Due to its strategic location, it faced constant attacks from Zionist militias for five months, starting in December 1947. A major Haganah attack on January 18, 1…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/salama.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-'Abbasiyya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-abbasiyya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-abbasiyya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Formerly known as al-Yahudiyya ('the Jewish town'), this large village east of Jaffa was renamed al-'Abbasiyya in 1932. It had a thriving agricultural economy. The Irgun (IZL) militia first attacked in December 1947, planting bombs in the village. The village was finally occupied by Irgun forces on May 4, 1948, during…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-abbasiyya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Yazur]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/yazur</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/yazur</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[An ancient village on the strategic Jaffa-Ramla highway, Yazur was known since Canaanite times. It was subjected to a series of raids and attacks starting in December 1947. In one notable incident on January 22, 1948, Zionist militia bombed a coffeehouse, killing at least six villagers. The Givati Brigade occupied the…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/yazur.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Lajjun]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-lajjun</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-lajjun</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A strategically vital village near the ancient site of Megiddo (Armageddon), al-Lajjun stood on the ruins of the Roman city of Legio. It was captured by the Golani Brigade on May 30, 1948, shortly after British forces withdrew from a nearby police fort. The Haganah's operational orders for the assault, as documented b…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-lajjun.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Lifta]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/lifta</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/lifta</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[An ancient and architecturally stunning village at the western entrance to Jerusalem, identified with the biblical town of Nephtoah. Lifta's depopulation began early, marking one of the first instances of ethnic cleansing in the Jerusalem corridor. On December 28, 1947, the Stern Gang (Lehi) and Irgun militias attacke…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/lifta.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Deir Yassin]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/deir-yassin</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/deir-yassin</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A prosperous village on a hill west of Jerusalem, Deir Yassin was known for its limestone quarries and had established a non-aggression pact with neighboring Jewish communities. On April 9, 1948, despite its declared neutrality, the village was attacked by over 120 men from the Irgun (IZL) and Lehi (Stern Gang) militi…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/deir-yassin.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Qastal]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-qastal</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-qastal</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small but strategically vital village built around a Roman and Crusader fort (Castellum) that commanded the main Jaffa-Jerusalem highway. Al-Qastal became the site of one of the most famous battles of the 1948 war. It was a critical target of Operation Nachshon, the Haganah's first major offensive to break the siege…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-qastal.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Maliha]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-maliha</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-maliha</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A large suburban village southwest of Jerusalem, known for its fine stone houses and agricultural land. The depopulation of al-Maliha occurred in stages. A first wave of residents fled in fear after the Deir Yassin massacre in April 1948. The village was finally attacked and occupied on the night of July 13-14, 1948,…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-maliha.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Qalunya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/qalunya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/qalunya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village on the main Jaffa-Jerusalem highway, identified with the Roman settlement of Colonia Amosa and the biblical town of Motza. It was a primary target of Operation Nachshon due to its strategic position. On April 11, 1948, following the battle for al-Qastal, Palmach units from the Harel Brigade entered Qalunya.…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/qalunya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Saris]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/saris</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/saris</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village perched on a high plateau west of Jerusalem, Saris was known for its olive groves and grain fields. It was attacked and demolished by the Haganah's Harel Brigade on April 16, 1948, during Operation Nachshon. The attack was part of a broader strategy to clear the Bab al-Wad area of its Palestinian population.…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/saris.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Suba]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/suba</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/suba</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Located on a strategic mountaintop west of Jerusalem, Suba was built within the ruins of the formidable Crusader fortress of Belmont. Its houses were clustered inside the castle's ancient walls. The village was captured on the night of July 12-13, 1948, by the Harel Brigade during Operation Dani. According to an Assoc…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/suba.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Bayt Mahsir]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/bayt-mahsir</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/bayt-mahsir</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A large village on a high ridge overlooking the coastal plain, Bayt Mahsir was a Palestinian stronghold that controlled access to the Bab al-Wad (Sha'ar HaGai) pass, a critical point on the Jerusalem road. It was captured by the Palmach's Harel Brigade on May 11, 1948, after three nights of fierce attacks during Opera…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/bayt-mahsir.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Kasla]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/kasla</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/kasla</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village situated on a mountaintop west of Jerusalem, Kasla is identified with the biblical city of Chesalon. It was depopulated during Operation Dani and subsequently 'cleansed' on July 16-18, 1948, by the Harel Brigade as part of an effort to widen the corridor to Jerusalem. Most villagers had either left earlier d…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/kasla.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Qula]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/qula</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/qula</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A strategically important village with a history stretching back to the Crusaders, who built a fortress there, Qula was a key objective during Operation Dani. It was first captured by the Alexandroni Brigade on July 10, 1948. However, the Jordanian Arab Legion launched a fierce counter-attack and recaptured it. It was…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/qula.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Isdud]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/isdud</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/isdud</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[An ancient and large village built on the site of the biblical Philistine city of Ashdod, Isdud was a key commercial and agricultural center on the southern coastal plain. During the 1948 war, it became a key frontline position occupied by the Egyptian army. As a result, it was subjected to heavy and repeated aerial a…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/isdud.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Faluja]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-faluja</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-faluja</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A large village that became internationally known as the site of the 'Faluja pocket,' where 4,000 Egyptian troops, including a young officer named Gamal Abdel Nasser, were besieged by Israeli forces for several months. The 1949 Armistice Agreement signed between Israel and Egypt explicitly stipulated that the 3,140 Pa…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-faluja.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Iraq Suwaydan]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/iraq-suwaydan</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/iraq-suwaydan</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[The strategic importance of Iraq Suwaydan was defined entirely by the formidable British police station (a Tegart fort) that dominated the village and the surrounding landscape. This fort became a key stronghold for the Egyptian army. Israeli forces launched eight separate and costly attempts to capture the fort betwe…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/iraq-suwaydan.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Masmiyya al-Kabira]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-masmiyya-al-kabira</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-masmiyya-al-kabira</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Masmiyya al-Kabira ('the large Masmiyya') was a major village located at a critical road junction on the southern coastal plain. It had a vibrant community with a mosque, two elementary schools, and a thriving market. Its inhabitants were primarily engaged in agriculture, cultivating grain and citrus. The village w…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-masmiyya-al-kabira.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Saffuriyya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/saffuriyya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/saffuriyya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[The largest and most prominent village in the Nazareth sub-district, Saffuriyya was built on a strategic hill over the ruins of the ancient Roman-Jewish capital of Galilee, Sepphoris. It was a thriving agricultural center with a rich history, a large mosque, a convent, and an orphanage. The village was occupied on the…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/saffuriyya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Mujaydil]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-mujaydil</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-mujaydil</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A large mixed Muslim and Christian village strategically located on the Nazareth-Haifa highway, al-Mujaydil was known for its trade and agriculture. It was occupied by the Golani Brigade on July 14-15, 1948, during the early stages of Operation Dekel. The attack on al-Mujaydil served as a strategic diversion for the m…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-mujaydil.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ma'lul]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/malul</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/malul</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A predominantly Christian village west of Nazareth, Ma'lul had a history dating back to at least the Roman era. Its residents were known for their close social and economic ties with Nazareth. The village was occupied on July 15, 1948, during Operation Dekel, just one day before the capture of Nazareth itself. Its inh…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/malul.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA['Allar]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/allar</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/allar</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village perched on a rocky hill in the Jerusalem corridor, 'Allar's economy was based on agriculture, primarily grains, vegetables, and olives from which oil was pressed in a local mill. The village was depopulated on October 22, 1948, during Operation ha-Har, an offensive by the Harel Brigade aimed at clearing the…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/allar.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA['Aqqur]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/aqqur</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/aqqur</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village situated in the Jerusalem mountains, 'Aqqur was depopulated on July 13-14, 1948, during Operation Dani. Its capture was part of a broader clearing operation in the Jerusalem corridor conducted by the Harel Brigade. Like its neighbors, the villagers were either expelled or fled in terror from the advanc…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/aqqur.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA['Artuf]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/artuf</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/artuf</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village located near the Jewish settlement of Hartuv, 'Artuf had a complex history of interaction with its neighbors. The village was depopulated on July 17-18, 1948, during Operation Dani, as the Harel Brigade expanded its control west of Jerusalem. The villagers were driven out, and their homes were subseque…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/artuf.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Beit 'Itab]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/beit-itab</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/beit-itab</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Built on the remains of an ancient Crusader fortress, Beit 'Itab was a village with a commanding view of the surrounding hills. It was a known stronghold for Palestinian fighters during the war. The village was captured on October 21, 1948, during Operation ha-Har by the Harel Brigade. After a battle, the remaining in…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/beit-itab.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Beit Umm al-Mays]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/beit-umm-al-mays</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/beit-umm-al-mays</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village situated on a mountain slope, Beit Umm al-Mays was known for its springs and agricultural terraces. It was depopulated around July 1, 1948, during the fighting of Operation Dani. Its proximity to other captured villages and the general offensive by the Harel Brigade led to its evacuation and subsequent…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/beit-umm-al-mays.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Burayj]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-burayj</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-burayj</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village named after a Crusader tower ('al-Burj'), al-Burayj was located in the foothills of the Jerusalem mountains. The village was depopulated on October 1, 1948, during the fighting that followed Operation An-Far. Its capture by the Givati Brigade was part of an effort to link up with forces in the Jerusale…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-burayj.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Deir 'Amr]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/deir-amr</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/deir-amr</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Named after a monastery that once stood on the site, Deir 'Amr was a village built on a mountain slope and known for its olive and fruit trees. The village was depopulated on July 14, 1948, during Operation Dani, as the Harel Brigade advanced through the Jerusalem corridor. The villagers were forced to flee, and their…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/deir-amr.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Deir Aban]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/deir-aban</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/deir-aban</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A large village located on the western slopes of the Hebron mountains, Deir Aban had a long history and contained the tomb of a revered local figure. It was captured late in the war, on October 20, 1948, during Operation ha-Har. The Harel Brigade attacked the village, forcing its residents to flee eastwards towards Be…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/deir-aban.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Deir al-Hawa]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/deir-al-hawa</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/deir-al-hawa</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Meaning 'Monastery of the Wind,' Deir al-Hawa was a village perched on a high mountain, making it a natural defensive position. It was attacked and captured on October 20, 1948, by the Harel Brigade as part of Operation ha-Har. According to Israeli military reports, after capturing the village, the soldiers 'blew up'…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/deir-al-hawa.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Deir al-Sheikh]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/deir-al-sheikh</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/deir-al-sheikh</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village in the Jerusalem mountains known for its prominent shrine to a Sufi leader, Shaykh Badr. The shrine, with its large dome, was an important local landmark. The village was captured on October 21, 1948, during Operation ha-Har. Its capture by the Harel Brigade led to the expulsion of its residents. While most…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/deir-al-sheikh.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Deir Rafat]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/deir-rafat</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/deir-rafat</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Deir Rafat was a small agricultural village. It should not be confused with the nearby Latin Patriarchate monastery of the same name, which still exists. The Palestinian village was depopulated on July 17-18, 1948, during Operation Dani, as Israeli forces worked to secure and widen their control over the Jerusalem cor…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/deir-rafat.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ishwa']]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/ishwa</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/ishwa</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village located in a valley at the foot of the Jerusalem mountains, Ishwa' was known for its grain cultivation. It was depopulated on July 17-18, 1948, during Operation Dani. The Harel Brigade captured the village as part of its offensive to control the area. The villagers were expelled, and their homes were subsequ…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/ishwa.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA['Islin]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/islin</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/islin</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village in the Jerusalem foothills, 'Islin was depopulated on July 18, 1948, during Operation Dani. Its capture was part of the same sweep by the Harel Brigade that took the neighboring village of Ishwa'. Its residents were forced to flee from the advancing army. Following the expulsion, the village was destro…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/islin.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Jura]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-jura</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-jura</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village situated on the western slopes of a mountain, overlooking the coastal plain from a distance, al-Jura was a short distance from Ein Karem. Its population began to flee in April 1948, terrified by the news of the Deir Yassin massacre nearby. The village was finally occupied on July 11, 1948, by Irgun and Lehi…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-jura.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Lawz, Khirbat]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-lawz-khirbat</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-lawz-khirbat</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Meaning 'the ruin of almonds,' Khirbat al-Lawz was a village built on a steep mountain slope. The village was depopulated on July 13-14, 1948, during Operation Dani. The Harel Brigade captured it as part of its campaign to 'cleanse' the Jerusalem corridor. The villagers were expelled, and their homes were later destro…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-lawz-khirbat.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Qabu]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-qabu</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-qabu</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village located in the mountainous terrain southwest of Jerusalem, al-Qabu's economy was tied to agriculture. It was captured on October 22, 1948, by the Harel Brigade during Operation ha-Har. This offensive was designed to clear a broad swath of territory, and al-Qabu was one of many villages depopulated duri…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-qabu.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ras Abu 'Ammar]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/ras-abu-ammar</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/ras-abu-ammar</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village situated on a mountain top, Ras Abu 'Ammar was known for its agricultural produce, which it sold in Jerusalem and Bethlehem. It was captured on October 21, 1948, by the Harel Brigade during Operation ha-Har. The capture of the village was part of a systematic campaign to depopulate the entire region. The vil…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/ras-abu-ammar.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Sar'a]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/sara</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/sara</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Identified with the biblical town of Zorah, Sar'a was a village with a long history, containing a shrine to the prophet Samson. It was captured on July 13-14, 1948, by the Harel Brigade during Operation Dani. The assault on Sar'a was part of a wider offensive to secure the area around Bab al-Wad. The villagers were ex…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/sara.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Abu al-Fadl]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/abu-al-fadl</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/abu-al-fadl</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village near the large Sarafand military base, Abu al-Fadl was inhabited by people from various clans, many of whom worked at the base. It was depopulated in May 1948 during Operation Barak, an offensive by the Givati Brigade aimed at clearing Palestinian villages south of Tel Aviv. The operation's orders were…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/abu-al-fadl.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Abu Shusha]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/abu-shusha</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/abu-shusha</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Situated near the archaeological mound of Tel Gezer, Abu Shusha was a village whose inhabitants farmed grain, vegetables, and fruit. It was captured on May 14, 1948, by the Givati Brigade during Operation Makkabi. A massacre occurred in the village after its capture. According to Israeli military archives and survivor…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/abu-shusha.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Na'ani]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-naani</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-naani</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village situated on the coastal plain, al-Na'ani's residents were primarily engaged in agriculture, cultivating grain, sesame, and fruit, particularly citrus. The village was located near the main highway and railway line. It was captured by the Givati Brigade on May 14, 1948, during Operation Barak, an offensive de…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-naani.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Qubab]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-qubab</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-qubab</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Located on high ground overlooking the coastal plain, al-Qubab was a large and strategically important village. Its inhabitants were known for their stone quarrying and agriculture. The village was attacked and captured on May 15, 1948, during Operation Makkabi. After its capture by the Givati Brigade, there were repo…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-qubab.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Barriyya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-barriyya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-barriyya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village on the coastal plain whose economy was based on grain, vegetable, and fruit farming. Al-Barriyya was depopulated on July 10, 1948, during Operation Dani, in the period known as the 'Ten Days' of fighting between the first and second truces. The village was captured by the Givati Brigade. While some sou…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-barriyya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Maghar]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-maghar</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-maghar</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Maghar was a large village known for its distinctive houses built into a hillside, giving it its name ('The Caves'). The village had a diverse population and a rich history. It was captured on May 15, 1948, by the Givati Brigade during Operation Barak. According to historical accounts, a massacre occurred in the vi…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-maghar.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Idnibba]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/idnibba</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/idnibba</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village located in the rolling hills of the Shephelah, Idnibba's livelihood depended on agriculture, particularly cereals and olive trees. It was depopulated on July 9-10, 1948, during Operation An-Far. Its capture by the Givati Brigade was part of the offensive aimed at blocking the advance of the Egyptian army. Th…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/idnibba.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Ajanjul]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/ajanjul</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/ajanjul</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village in the Ramle sub-district, Ajanjul's existence was tied to the land and agriculture. It was depopulated during the summer of 1948, likely in July during the widespread Israeli offensives in the area, such as Operation Dani or An-Far. The specific details of its capture are sparse, as it was one of many…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/ajanjul.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Haditha]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-haditha</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-haditha</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Haditha was a village with ancient origins, mentioned by the Roman historian Josephus. It was located near the city of Lydda. The village was captured on July 12, 1948, by the Yiftach Brigade as part of Operation Dani. Its capture occurred in conjunction with the infamous assault on Lydda and Ramla, which involved…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-haditha.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Khayma]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-khayma</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-khayma</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village situated on a high, conical hill, al-Khayma was depopulated on July 9-10, 1948, during Operation An-Far. The operation's objective was to clear the area and create a wedge between Egyptian and Jordanian forces. The Givati Brigade captured the village, and its inhabitants were expelled. The village was later…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-khayma.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Khulda]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/khulda</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/khulda</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village on the southern coastal plain, Khulda became a frontline position early in the war. The village was first attacked in April 1948, and a number of its houses were blown up by Haganah forces. The final depopulation occurred on July 12, 1948, during Operation Dani. Its capture by the Yiftach Brigade was part of…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/khulda.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Kunayyisa]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-kunayyisa</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-kunayyisa</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Meaning 'The Little Church,' al-Kunayyisa was a village located on rolling terrain. It was depopulated on July 9-10, 1948, during Operation An-Far. The Givati Brigade captured the village as it pushed to isolate Egyptian forces in the south. The villagers were expelled from their homes, and the village was subsequentl…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-kunayyisa.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Mansura]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-mansura</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-mansura</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village whose name means 'The Victorious,' al-Mansura was depopulated during the summer of 1948. It was likely captured in July by the Givati Brigade during the major offensives in the area. Like many smaller villages, its specific capture is not heavily documented, but it was part of the general sweep that et…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-mansura.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Nabi Rubin]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/nabi-rubin</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/nabi-rubin</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Nabi Rubin was not just a village but also a major religious and cultural site, home to a large shrine dedicated to the Prophet Reuben (Nabi Rubin). The site hosted a famous annual festival, or 'mawsim,' that drew tens of thousands of Palestinians from all over the country for weeks of religious ceremonies, trade, and…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/nabi-rubin.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Qazaza]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/qazaza</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/qazaza</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village situated on a low hill, Qazaza's economy revolved around agriculture. It was depopulated on July 9-10, 1948, during Operation An-Far. Captured by the Givati Brigade, its inhabitants were expelled as part of the broader military goal of clearing the southern coastal plain. The village was completely destroyed…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/qazaza.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Sajad]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/sajad</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/sajad</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Sajad was a small village whose lands were primarily used for cereal cultivation. It was depopulated on July 9-10, 1948, during Operation An-Far. The village was captured by the Givati Brigade during its push to control the area and block Egyptian forces. The inhabitants were expelled, and the village was destroyed. T…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/sajad.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Saydun]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/saydun</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/saydun</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village named after the ancient Lebanese city of Sidon, from where its founders were said to have originated. Saydun was depopulated in the summer of 1948, likely during the major Israeli offensives in July. Its capture was part of the general ethnic cleansing of the Ramle sub-district. After its inhabitants w…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/saydun.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Shahma]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/shahma</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/shahma</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Shahma was a small agricultural village on the southern coastal plain. It was depopulated on May 9, 1948, relatively early in the war, during Operation Barak. The Givati Brigade's orders for the operation involved the expulsion of Palestinian communities to secure the area around future Israeli settlements. After its…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/shahma.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Shilta]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/shilta</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/shilta</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Located in the Latrun area, Shilta was one of several villages destroyed during Operation Dani in July 1948. After capturing Lydda and Ramla, Israeli forces pushed into the Latrun area, which was designated as a 'no-man's land' in the armistice agreement. However, Israel occupied and destroyed the villages within it t…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/shilta.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Tina]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-tina</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-tina</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Tina was a village on the southern coastal plain whose residents were farmers. It was depopulated on July 8-9, 1948, at the very beginning of the 'Ten Days' offensive between the two truces. The village was captured by the Givati Brigade during Operation An-Far. Its residents were expelled, and the village was dest…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-tina.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Tira Dandan]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/tira-dandan</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/tira-dandan</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Located north of the city of Tulkarm, Tira Dandan (also known as Tira al-Lawz) was a large village with a long history. It was depopulated in May 1948. Its proximity to the coastal area made it an early target for Zionist forces seeking to create a contiguous Jewish-held territory. After its inhabitants were expelled,…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/tira-dandan.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Umm Kalkha]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/umm-kalkha</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/umm-kalkha</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small agricultural village, Umm Kalkha was depopulated on July 9-10, 1948, during Operation An-Far. Its capture by the Givati Brigade was part of the same offensive that took nearby villages like Sajad and al-Kunayyisa. The villagers were expelled from their homes, and the village was later demolished. Its lands wer…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/umm-kalkha.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Imara]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-imara</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-imara</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Imara was a Bedouin village in the northern Negev desert. It was one of many Bedouin localities whose inhabitants were forcibly displaced during and after the 1948 war. It was captured during Operation Yoav in late October 1948. Following the capture of the area, the residents were expelled, part of a wider policy…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-imara.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Jammama]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/jammama</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/jammama</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village in the northern Negev, Jammama was captured on May 22, 1948, by the Negev Brigade during Operation Barak. The operation aimed to drive out Palestinian communities from the areas surrounding Jewish settlements in the south. The villagers were expelled from their homes, and the village was destroyed. The Israe…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/jammama.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Khalasa]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-khalasa</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-khalasa</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Khalasa was a Bedouin center on the site of the ancient Nabatean city of Elusa. It was a key location in the Negev desert. The village was captured during Operation Yoav in October 1948. Following the Israeli army's occupation of the area, the inhabitants were forcibly expelled, part of the systematic removal of th…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-khalasa.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Ashrafiyya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-ashrafiyya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-ashrafiyya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Located in the fertile Baysan Valley, al-Ashrafiyya was a village whose residents were primarily farmers. It was captured on May 12, 1948, by the Golani Brigade during Operation Gideon. This operation was designed to seize control of the entire Baysan Valley. Following its capture, the villagers were expelled, and the…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-ashrafiyya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Bira]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-bira</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-bira</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village situated in the Baysan Valley, al-Bira was known for its numerous springs and fertile lands. It was captured by the Golani Brigade on May 16, 1948, during Operation Gideon. The operation aimed to create a continuous strip of Israeli-controlled territory and preempt the entry of Arab armies. The villagers wer…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-bira.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Fatur]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-fatur</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-fatur</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village situated on the floodplain of the Jordan River, al-Fatur's economy was based on agriculture. It was depopulated in May 1948 during Operation Gideon, an offensive by the Golani Brigade designed to seize control of the entire Baysan Valley before the end of the British Mandate. The operation's orders inc…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-fatur.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Farwana]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/farwana</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/farwana</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Farwana was a village located just south of the city of Baysan, with its economy centered on the cultivation of grains, vegetables, and bananas. The village was captured on May 11-12, 1948, by the Golani Brigade during Operation Gideon. The operation aimed to isolate Baysan and clear the surrounding area of its Palest…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/farwana.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Ghazzawiyya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-ghazzawiyya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-ghazzawiyya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Comprised of a cluster of Bedouin settlements in the fertile Baysan Valley, al-Ghazzawiyya's population were primarily tenant farmers. The area was captured by the Golani Brigade on May 20, 1948. Following the occupation, many of the residents were expelled, while others were subjected to a campaign of harassment and…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-ghazzawiyya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Hamidiyya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-hamidiyya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-hamidiyya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Named after Ottoman Sultan Abdul Hamid II, al-Hamidiyya was a village in the Baysan Valley known for its agriculture. It was captured by the Golani Brigade on May 12, 1948, during Operation Gideon. Like other villages in the valley, its capture was part of a systematic plan to create a 'cleansed' and contiguous territ…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-hamidiyya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Hamra]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-hamra</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-hamra</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village in the southern Baysan Valley, al-Hamra's inhabitants were farmers who cultivated the surrounding fertile lands. The village was depopulated in May 1948 during the Golani Brigade's sweep of the valley in Operation Gideon. Its residents were forced to flee from the advancing Israeli forces, and the vill…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-hamra.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Jabbul]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/jabbul</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/jabbul</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Jabbul was an agricultural village located on the plain of the Baysan Valley. It was captured by the Golani Brigade on May 12, 1948, during Operation Gideon. The operation's success depended on the rapid depopulation of the Palestinian villages in the valley to create a secure zone. The inhabitants of Jabbul were expe…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/jabbul.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Kafra]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/kafra</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/kafra</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village situated on the southern bank of the Jalud River, Kafra was known for its grain and vegetable crops. It was captured by the Golani Brigade on May 16, 1948, during Operation Gideon. The capture was part of the final phase of the operation to consolidate control over the entire valley. The villagers were expel…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/kafra.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Kawkab al-Hawa]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/kawkab-al-hawa</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/kawkab-al-hawa</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Perched on a strategic hilltop overlooking the Jordan Valley, Kawkab al-Hawa was built on the site of the magnificent Crusader fortress of Belvoir. The village was involved in fighting early on and was captured on May 21, 1948, by the Golani Brigade. Its strategic location made it a key military objective. The village…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/kawkab-al-hawa.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Khunayzir]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-khunayzir</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-khunayzir</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village located in the northern part of the Baysan Valley, al-Khunayzir's economy was tied to agriculture. It was captured by the Golani Brigade around May 20, 1948, during Operation Gideon. The offensive systematically cleared the valley's villages, and al-Khunayzir was no exception. Its inhabitants were driven out…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-khunayzir.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Masil al-Jizl]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/masil-al-jizl</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/masil-al-jizl</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village in the southern end of the Baysan Valley, Masil al-Jizl was depopulated on May 31, 1948. Its capture came shortly after the main offensive of Operation Gideon, as Israeli forces consolidated their control over the area. The villagers were expelled, and their homes were destroyed. The Israeli settlement…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/masil-al-jizl.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Murassas]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-murassas</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-murassas</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Murassas was a village situated on high ground, giving it a commanding view of the surrounding plains. It was captured on May 16, 1948, by the Golani Brigade during Operation Gideon. The capture of the village was part of the push to secure the northern part of the valley. After its inhabitants were expelled, the v…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-murassas.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Qumya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/qumya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/qumya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A village of Circassian origin, Qumya was located in the northern Baysan Valley. Though the Circassian community in Palestine generally tried to remain neutral, they were ultimately targeted. Qumya was captured by the Golani Brigade on May 15, 1948, during Operation Gideon. Its inhabitants were expelled, and the villa…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/qumya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Sakhina]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-sakhina</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-sakhina</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Named 'the hot one' because of its warm springs, al-Sakhina was a village just southwest of Baysan city. It was captured on May 12, 1948, by the Golani Brigade during Operation Gideon. Its proximity to the city made it an early target in the campaign to isolate and capture Baysan. The villagers were expelled, and the…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-sakhina.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Samiriyya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-samiriyya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-samiriyya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Samiriyya was a village in the Baysan Valley that was depopulated during the later stages of Operation Gideon. It was captured around May 27-28, 1948, by the Golani Brigade. The operation's goal was total control of the valley, which necessitated the removal of its Palestinian population. The inhabitants of al-Sami…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-samiriyya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Sirin]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/sirin</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/sirin</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Located on a strategic basalt hill, Sirin was a village that had a history of resisting British forces during the 1936-39 Arab revolt. It was captured on May 12, 1948, by the Golani Brigade. An earlier attack by the Palmach in February had already caused some residents to flee. After its final capture, the remaining v…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/sirin.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Tall al-Shawk]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/tall-al-shawk</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/tall-al-shawk</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village just south of Baysan city, Tall al-Shawk was depopulated on May 12, 1948. It was captured by the Golani Brigade during the initial phase of Operation Gideon. The operation focused on clearing the villages surrounding the city of Baysan to facilitate its capture. The villagers were expelled, and their h…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/tall-al-shawk.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Umm 'Ajra]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/umm-ajra</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/umm-ajra</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Umm 'Ajra was a village in the Baysan Valley known for its agriculture. It was one of the many villages systematically depopulated by the Golani Brigade during Operation Gideon. It was captured around May 20, 1948. After its inhabitants were driven out, the village was completely destroyed. The Israeli settlement of S…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/umm-ajra.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Zab'a]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/zaba</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/zaba</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Zab'a was a village in the Baysan Valley that had been a site of archaeological interest, containing ancient mosaics. It was captured by the Golani Brigade in May 1948, during Operation Gideon. The operation's swift and systematic nature ensured the entire valley was ethnically cleansed. The inhabitants of Zab'a were…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/zaba.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Abu Shusha]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/abu-shusha</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/abu-shusha</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Located on the edge of the Jezreel Valley, Abu Shusha was a village whose inhabitants were primarily farmers. It was captured on April 9, 1948, during the Battle of Mishmar HaEmek. The Haganah's operational orders for the area were to 'cleanse' the surrounding villages. Following its capture by the Golani Brigade, the…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/abu-shusha.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Abu Zurayq]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/abu-zurayq</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/abu-zurayq</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small village at the foot of Mount Carmel, Abu Zurayq's economy was based on farming grains and vegetables. It was depopulated on April 12, 1948, during the Battle of Mishmar HaEmek. As part of a counter-offensive, Haganah forces were ordered to capture and destroy the surrounding Palestinian villages. Abu Zurayq wa…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/abu-zurayq.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Balad al-Shaykh]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/balad-al-shaykh</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/balad-al-shaykh</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A large and important village at the foot of Mount Carmel, Balad al-Shaykh was the burial site of Izz ad-Din al-Qassam, the revered Syrian cleric and revolutionary leader. On the night of December 31, 1947, in retaliation for the killing of Jewish workers at the nearby oil refinery, Haganah forces carried out a bloody…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/balad-al-shaykh.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Barrat Qisarya]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/barrat-qisarya</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/barrat-qisarya</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[A small Bedouin settlement near the ancient Roman ruins of Caesarea, Barrat Qisarya's inhabitants were farmers and laborers. The community was depopulated in February 1948. Haganah forces, under the pretext of security, began systematically demolishing houses in the area, forcing the residents to leave. This was an ea…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/barrat-qisarya.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Butaymat]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/butaymat</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/butaymat</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Butaymat was a small village in the hills southeast of Haifa. It was depopulated in April 1948, during the series of attacks and counter-attacks around the Jewish settlement of Mishmar HaEmek. The village was one of several in the area that was cleared by Haganah forces to create a secure zone. Its inhabitants were fo…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/butaymat.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Hawsha]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/hawsha</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/hawsha</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Hawsha was a village located on a hill in the western Galilee, part of a cluster of villages that included al-Kasayir and Khirbat al-Damun. It was captured on April 16, 1948, by the Carmeli Brigade. The battle for Hawsha was fierce, with villagers putting up a strong defense alongside the Arab Liberation Army. After i…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/hawsha.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[al-Jalama]]></title>
      <link>https://fromtheriver.org/archive/al-jalama</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">villages/al-jalama</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[Al-Jalama was a village located at a strategic crossroads east of Haifa. It was captured on April 30, 1948, by the Carmeli Brigade during Operation Bi'ur Hametz ('Passover Cleaning'), the same offensive that secured Haifa. The capture of al-Jalama helped to secure the main road and cut off Haifa from the east. The vil…]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 03:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <enclosure url="https://fromtheriver.org/og/al-jalama.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml" />
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
